American Movie is a documentary, comedy film directed by Chris Smith.
American Movie documents the story of filmmaker Mark
Borchardt, his mission, and his dream.
Spanning over two years of intense struggle with his film, his family, financial decline, and spiritual crisis,
American Movie is a portrayal of ambition, obsession, excess, and one man's quest for the American Dream.
Filmmaker, played by Mark Borchardt.
Friend / Musician, played by Mike Schank.
Actor in 'Coven', played by Tom Schimmels.
Mark's Mom, played by Monica Borchardt.
Mark's Brother, played by Alex Borchardt.
Mark's Brother, played by Chris Borchardt.
American Movie is a 1999 American documentary film directed by Chris Smith, produced
by Smith and Sarah Price, and edited by Jun Diaz and Barry Poltermann.
Filmed between September 1995 and August 1997, American Movie documents the making of
Coven, an independent short horror film directed by Mark Borchardt.
Produced for the purpose of raising capital for Northwestern, a feature film Borchardt intends to make, Coven suffers from numerous setbacks, including
poor financing, a lack of planning, Borchardt's alcoholism, and the ineptitude of the friends and family he enlists as his production team.
The documentary follows Borchardt's filmmaking process, interspersed
with footage from both of Borchardt's developing projects.
American Movie received positive reviews and won the Grand Jury Prize
for Documentary at the 1999 Sundance Film Festival.
It has since become a cult film.
The film explores themes of underdog, obsession, wisconsin, beer, ambition.
The tone is lighthearted and intense.